"Houston, we have a problem."
Apollo 13 is a drama, history film directed by Ron Howard.
The true story of technical troubles that scuttle the Apollo 13 lunar mission in 1970, risking the lives of
astronaut Jim Lovell and his crew, with the failed journey turning into a thrilling saga of heroism.
Drifting more than 200,000 miles from Earth, the astronauts work
furiously with the ground crew to avert tragedy.
Jim Lovell, played by Tom Hanks.
Fred Haise, played by Bill Paxton.
Jack Swigert, played by Kevin Bacon.
Ken Mattingly, played by Gary Sinise.
Gene Kranz, played by Ed Harris.
Marilyn Lovell, played by Kathleen Quinlan.
Apollo 13 is a 1995 American docudrama film directed by Ron Howard and starring Tom
Hanks, Kevin Bacon, Bill Paxton, Gary Sinise, Ed Harris and Kathleen Quinlan.
The screenplay by William Broyles Jr.
and Al Reinert dramatizes the aborted 1970 Apollo 13 lunar mission and is an adaptation of the 1994 book
Lost Moon: The Perilous Voyage of Apollo 13, by astronaut Jim Lovell and Jeffrey Kluger.
The film tells the story of astronauts Lovell, Jack Swigert, and Fred Haise aboard the ill-fated Apollo 13 for
the United States' fifth crewed mission to the Moon, which was intended to be the third to land.
En route, an on-board explosion deprives their spacecraft of much of its oxygen supply and electrical power, which forces NASA's flight
controllers to abandon the Moon landing and improvise scientific and mechanical solutions to get the three astronauts to Earth safely.
Howard went to great lengths to create a technically accurate movie, employing NASA's assistance in astronaut and flight-controller training for his cast and
obtaining permission to film scenes aboard a reduced-gravity aircraft for realistic depiction of the weightlessness experienced by the astronauts in space.
Released in theaters by Universal Pictures in the United States on June 30, 1995, Apollo 13 received critical acclaim and
was nominated for nine Academy Awards, including Best Picture (winning for Best Film Editing and Best Sound).
The film also won the Screen Actors Guild Award for Outstanding Performance by a
Cast in a Motion Picture, as well as two British Academy Film Awards.
In total, the film grossed over $355 million worldwide during its theatrical
releases and becoming the third-highest-grossing film of 1995.
It is listed in The New York Times Guide to the
Best 1,000 Movies Ever Made (2004).
In 2023, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically or aesthetically significant."
The film explores themes of rescue, florida, race against time, moon, nasa.
The tone is emotional and intense.